Finding Aid for the Miriam Matthews photograph collection, 1781-1989 LSC.1889
UCLA Library Special Collections
Miriam Matthews photograph collection
1781-1989
UCLA Library Special Collections
Matthews, Miriam
LSC.1889
50 linear feet (98 boxes)
The Miriam Matthews photograph Collection consists of 4,600 black and white photographs of varying sizes, negatives, captions and descriptions from museum exhibitions, and a slide carousel. The collection reflects Matthews' dedication to the preservation of African American history in Los Angeles. The chronology of the scenes and people depicted in this collection spans from the Spanish founding of the city in the late 18th century to the 1980s, with the bulk of the collection from the twentieth century. Key points of interest from the Spanish and Mexican eras include the founding Los Angeles pobladores of African descent, African American stagecoach drivers and overland guides to California, and the multiracial californio family of Pio Pico. Other points of interest after U.S. annexation in 1848 include the influx of middle class African Americans to Los Angeles between 1890 and 1915, as well as the churches, social, charitable, and fraternal organizations they formed during this period and through the 1980s. Matthews' collection also highlights those individuals who contributed to civil rights legislation and advocacy, those who were elected or appointed to government positions, popular entertainers, artists, and black-owned businesses. There is also substantial collection of photographs produced by black photographer Harry H. Adams, documenting life, politics, community service, and civil rights movement in Los Angeles in the 1960s.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
PORTIONS OF THIS COLLECTION HAVE BEEN DIGITIZED. Please consult digital facsimiles instead of originals.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift/purchase from Charles Matthews, Jr., 2011.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9969520863606533
Biography/History
Miriam Matthews was born in Pensacola, Florida on August 6, 1905 to Reuben and Fannie Matthews. Two years later the Matthews family moved to a neighborhood of European immigrants in Los Angeles, just south of downtown, where her father found work as a house painter. Matthews received her Bachelor's degree from University of California at Berkeley in 1926 and her librarian's certificate a year later. Matthews was hired as the first black librarian in California by the Los Angeles Public Library in 1927, despite attempts to prevent her from knowing the date of the Civil Service examination. After working for ten years at the Los Angeles Public Library without promotion, Matthews took a leave of absence to pursue a Masters degree in Library Science at the University of Chicago. She was then promoted to a position as a regional librarian, supervising the management of several libraries until her retirement in 1960. Early on in her career, Matthews discovered a small collection of books detailing the role of African Americans, and people of African descent, in the founding of Los Angeles and began building her own collection of books, manuscripts, and photographs. Her work in the preservation and exhibition of Los Angeles' black past continued long after her retirement.
Scope and Content
The prominent black families and individuals represented in this collection are organized using Matthews' chronology and terminology. The titles given to them, such as "founders," "settlers," and "pioneers" reflect the context and values in which Matthews lived. Those designated as Founders were the original pobladores, a group of mixed race colonists, who established the pueblo of Los Angeles for New Spain. Manuel Camero and Jose Moreno, both of African descent, are highlighted in this collection. The Early Settlers include those of Spanish, Mexican, or American origin, who arrived after the founding in 1781. Juan Fernando Reyes, the first black mayor of Los Angeles, and other Californios of African descent, in particular, Pio Pico, are highlighted in this series. The Pioneers refer to the African American men and women who migrated to Los Angeles at the turn of the century, seeking greater freedom and opportunity than the Jim Crow South offered. The twentieth-century figures highlighted by Matthews included those who worked for the expansion of civil and human rights, such as Loren Miller and Ralph Bunche.
Photographs of the daily lives of African Americans in Los Angeles include their involvement in churches, social organizations, civil rights movements, entertainment, sports and recreation, businesses and professions, parades, education, military, civil service, and street scenes.
Harry H. Adams was a photographer for the California Eagle and Los Angeles Sentinel newspapers, and for churches, organizations, and individuals within the black community. While his photographic career spanned from 1955 to 1988, the bulk of the collection housed here is from the 1960s and includes images of civil rights movements, churches, schools, business, entertainment, police, sports, and street scenes.
Material from museum and gallery exhibitions includes text, signage, and mounted photographs used at the California African American Museum, the California Museum of Industry, El Pueblo Historic Park, Los Angeles Public Library, and possibly other unidentified exhibitions. This series also includes a slide carousel and slides depicting the early history of African Americans in California.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Early California
Daily Life in Black Los Angeles and California
Black Photographers
Museum and Gallery Exhibitions
Prominent Individuals and Families
Related Material
Miriam Matthews Papers (Collection 1804). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Online Items Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Miriam Matthews Photograph Collection (1559 items)
Photographs.; African American women librarians -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archives.; Matthews, Miriam -- Archives
- Early California., 1781-1920.
  Scope and Contents note
  Men and women of African descent who ventured to Los Angeles, California, and the West before 1920. The first wave of migration arrived before the Santa Fe railroad connected to Los Angeles in 1885. The second wave arrived between 1890 and 1915 as Los Angeles experienced explosive growth.
  - Monuments, Murals, Exhibitions, and Anniversaries of Early Los Angeles., 1949-1981.
    Photographs of historical interpretations, anniversaries, and representations of early Los Angeles.
    - Photographs of diorama displays in Natural History Museum., 1781, 1846. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Photographs of two dioramas: first, of 22 adults and 22 children arriving at the site for the pueblo of Los Angeles on September 4, 1781; second, of the Battle of San Pasqual during the Mexican American War in 1846.
    - Prints of drawings of De Anza Expedition., 1774-1777. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Juan Bautista de Anza led the first expeditions of Spain to Alta California. Drawings by Carl Oscar Borc (1931) and Walter Francis (1909).
    - Founders Monument, El Pueblo de Los Angeles., 1981. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Founder's Monument, El Pueblo de Los Angeles Historic Park. Founders Plaque inscription; dedication of plaque by LA City Historical Society and Greater Boyle Heights Historical Bicentennial Committee; certificate presented to descendants of founders of Los Angeles, June 5, 1981.
    - Los Angeles, 175th Birthday., September 1956. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Print from poster of 175th anniversary of Los Angeles.
    - Golden State Mutual Life Mural, panel by Charles Alston., 1949. (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Photographic portrait of artist Charles Alston. Alston panel was entitled "The Negro in California History - Exploration and Colonization."
    - Golden State Mutual Life Mural, panel by Hale Woodruff., 1949. (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Photographic portrait of artist Hale Woodruff. Woodruff panel was entitled "The Negro in California History - Settlement and Development."
    - G.S.M. mural research tour with Charles Alston and Hale Woodruff., 1948. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Photographs of artists at Mission San Diego, a mining shaft in gold rush country, Beckwourth Pass.
    - G.S.M. Murals Conference and Dedication of artwork., 1949. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Photographs of artists, architects, and officers of Golden State Mutual Life Insurance at the unveiling of artwork, dedication, and conference.
  - Buildings and Ranchos., 1784-1888.
    Photographs of adobe buildings, Franciscan missions, houses, and ranchos. Mostly built in the mid-19th century.
    - Pico family properties. (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Includes photographs of adobe homes of Pio and Andres Pico in Whittier and Los Angeles. Pico house, hotel, in Los Angeles.
    - Owens family properties., 1869-1913. (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Includes photographs of homes of Robert Owens Sr. and Robert Curry Owens; Owens livery stables; plots of Owens property; Owens business block on Broadway (1898, 1904, 1913); view of Los Angeles in 1869.
    - Missions. (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Including Mission Dolores and drawings of Mission San Diego. Photograph of Santa Susana pass which connected Missions San Fernando and San Buenaventura.
    - Early California maps and photographs outside Los Angeles., 1846-1849. (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Includes San Francisco, Julian
  - Founders, Explorers, Travelers., 1527-1892.
    Images of first explorers of African descent to California; the pobladores and settlers of Los Angeles of African descent; gold rush miners; stagecoach drivers
    - Explorers of African descent., 1527-1844. (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Includes photo prints of drawings by Sam Patrick: Jacob Dodson of the John C. Fremont expeditions to California; York of the Lewis and Clark expedition; Estevanico, first person born in Africa to arrive in the present-day continental United States.
    - Manuel Camero, founder of Los Angeles, of African descent, and one of first city councilmen., 1781. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Manuel Camero served as Los Angeles regidor (city councilman) after arriving in 1781, he died in 1819. From a drawing by Samuel Patrick, former Los Angeles Times staff artist.
    - Jose and Maria Guadalupe Moreno, founders of Los Angeles of African descent, and their descendants., 1781. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Portrait of Jose and Maria Guadalupe Moreno is from a painting by an artist at the LA County Museum of Natural History. Includes, photograph of grandson, Manuel Moreno taken in LA in 1905 when he was 80 years old; photography of granddaughter, Catarina Moreno, wife of Andres Pico (credit: LA Museum of Natural History).
    - Luis and Maria Petra Quintero, founders of Los Angeles, of African descent., 1781. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      From painting by staff artist, LA County Museum of Natural History.
    - Family and descendants of Juan Francisco Reyes, alcalde, 1793-1795. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Son of Francisco Reyes, Ysidro Reyes, and his family. Grandson, Fernando Reyes. Great granddaughter, Regugio Reyes de Roberts. Great-great grandson Juan Chevez outside old adobe hacienda once owned by ancestor in 1920.
    - Stagecoach Drivers and Pony Express Riders., 1848-1892. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Photographic portraits of stagecoach drivers: Nathaniel Smith, Gus Thompson, and George Monroe. Portrait of William Robinson, Pony Express Rider from Stockton and gold mining communities.
    - James P. Beckwourth, mountain man, explorer, fur trader., b. 1798- d. 1866. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Portraits (both from drawings and photographs) of James Beckwourth, including one with hunting costume. Photographic portrait of his Indian wife.
    - Prints and negatives of Beckwourth trading post, Beckwourth Pass monument, and map. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Photographs and negatives of Beckwourth Pass monument with artists from Golden State Mutual mural; Beckwourth's trading post; map showing places named after him. Photo of Crow Indian Sun Dance (Beckwourth was given title of honorary chief of this tribe).
    - Gold Rush., 1849-1852. (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Photographs of African American miners during Gold Rush, mining site named "Nigger Bar," and sign for mining town of Timbuctoo named by African American miner.
  - Early Settlers Outside Los Angeles., 1800-1880.
    African American men and women who settled in California before 1880.
    - Elizabeth Neal and family., 1862, 1870. (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Elizabeth Neal San Francisco, circa 1870. Her daughter with husband James Lodge in San Jose, 1862
    - Frederick Sparrow., c. 1870. (Box 4, Folder 2)
      First black man to vote in Napa, Napa County in 1870.
    - Susan Wilson., c. 1860. (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Susan Wilson was brought to California in 1853 by ox-team from Missouri. Worked to pay for her freedom of self and three children.
    - Philip Bell., b. 1808 - d. 1889. (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Black journalist, newspaper editor, and civil rights advocate in San Francisco.
    - Alvin Coffey., c. 1849. (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Alvin Coffey, 49er and pioneer, two portraits
    - Early California African American pioneers. (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Includes Rev. J. B. Sanderson, Mamie Netherland, a Sacramento clubhouse, and descendants of black California pioneers.
    - Allen Light, document certifying he is free., 1827. (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Born in Philadelphia, citizen of the U.S.
    - Nate Harrison, pioneer in San Diego., c. 1823-1920. (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Nathan Harrison, his shack on Mount Palomar, and nearby monument.
    - Unidentified early Northern Californian portraits. (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Portraits by W. B. Ingersoll, photographer, Oakland, 19th century. Also, photo of school children.
    - Captain William Shorey, black whaling ship captain on the west coast between 1880-1900., 1880s-1890s. (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Photos of ships in harbor of SF Bay, Capt. William Shorey and his family, his daughter Victoria, and streets named after him.
    - Black sailors. (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Black sailors on ship with white officers; first steamship on Pacific coast/
    - David W. Ruggles, only black member of U.S. Grand Jury., 1878-1900. (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Includes photographs of U.S. Grand Jury, an elderly portrait, and his store.
    - John Grider, member of Bear Flag Party., c. 1849. (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Only black member of Vallejo Society of California Pioneers. The member of Bear Flag Party who secured the brown paint to paint the bear on the original flag. Includes photo of Bear Flag monument
    - James Henry Coleman, contractor and businessman in Redding, CA., b. 1889- d. 1949. (Box 4, Folder 14)
      Includes portraits of three children, his daughter as an adult, his mother, and himself with an unidentified man. Also photo of house under construction by his company.
    - William Leidesdorff, mixed race businessman in San Francisco., died 1848. (Box 4, Folder 15)
      Drawings of William Leidesdorff, his residence, and properties in San Francisco.
    - Mary Ellen Pleasant, entrepreneur and abolitionist of African descent. (Box 4, Folder 16)
      Portraits of Mary Ellen Pleasant and her family. Images relating to the business dealings and property operated by Pleasant and Thomas Bell. Grave and grave marker at Tulocay Cemetery in Napa. Portrait of her butler.
    - Eliza Davis, pioneer woman., undated. (Box 4, Folder 17)
      Eliza Davis, pioneer woman at cabin in Sonora, Tuolomne County
    - Unidentified black early Californians. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Israel Beal, Redlands pioneer., b. 1848- d. 1929. (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Beal helped in construction of the Redlands reservoir, pipelines and the original Big Bear Dam. He was a founding elder of Second Baptist church, officer of Redlands Mutual Benefit Association in 1892.
    - Binum family, pioneer family in Calaveras., 1850s. (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Includes photographs of Margaret (midwife and nurse) and her sons James and Lev (operated Bon Ton Chop House in San Andreas).
    - Folder number not used. (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - William E. Towns and family, San Francisco Bay Area., c. 1867- 1969. (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Includes portraits of William E. Towns, his wife Elizabeth Scott Towns, his son Henry Towns, and youngest son Royal E. Towns with a group of other California pioneers c. 1969. Also includes photograph of siblings Wallace, Ben, Nellie, and Henry Towns as children.
    - Beverly A. Johnson. (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Wilkerson family. (Box 4, Folder 24)
      Four young girls, Lompoc, California.
    - Mayme Mary C. Netherland. (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Portrait at a young age, and photograph of her birthplace.
  - Early Settlers Within Los Angeles., 1800-1880.
    African American men and women who settled in Los Angeles before 1880.
    - Charles Owens (son of Robert Owens Sr.) and wife Ellen Mason (daughter of Biddy Mason). (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Prominent early African American settlers Robert Owens and Biddy Mason bought and maintained substantial properties in Los Angeles. Robert Owens' son Charles, married Biddy Mason's daughter Ellen.
    - Robert Curry Owens, wife Anna Dugger, her Dugger family. (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Grandson of Biddy Mason, Robert Curry Owens and wife Anna (nee: Dugger). Robert Curry Owens' recollections of his grandfather. Photos of family at "Mother Goose Party" which they hosted.
    - Henry Owens (brother Robert Curry Owens) and wife Louise. (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Portraits of grandson of Biddy Mason, and his wife Louise.
    - Gladys Owens Smith and Manila Owens (daughters of Robert Curry Owens). (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Daughters of Robert Curry Owens and wife Anna Dugger. Includes childhood, travel, and costume photographs.
    - Unidentified photos, possible Mason/Owens families. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Biddy Mason and Robert Owens families Binder 1. (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Photographs from a binder compiled by Miriam Matthews. Includes images Biddy Mason, Robert Owens, and their families.
    - Mason/Owens Binder 2. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Early California historical small prints, both San Francisco and Los Angeles. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Includes Mr. and Mrs. Harry Johnson; Rt. Rev. T.M. Ward, the first ordained African Methodist Episcopal minister on the Pacific Coast; Rev. Charles Satchell; Laura Robinson; Mary Ellen Pleasant and family; Bear Flag monument; first steamboat in California; Congressman White; Sidney Dones real estate office; Don Pio Pico.
    - Benjamin Talbot. (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Portraits of Benjamin Talbot, his wife, and possibly his daughters.
    - Early settlers of Los Angeles., 1848-1885. (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Includes preacher and politician Peter Johnson, Beverly A. Johnson, children of William E. Towns, William Marcus and Moselle Moore, Don Antonio Coronel.
    - Pio Pico, last Mexican governor of California, and family., b. 1801- d. 1894. (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Portraits of Pio, wife, and two nieces; Pio Pico's tomb; Calendar showing ownership of land in Southern California by the Pico family; portraits of Andres Pico and his wife Catarina Moreno (same portrait in box 1, folder 3)
    - Portraits of Biddy Mason., b. 1818- d. 1891. (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Biddy Mason was brought to California as a slave in a wagon train. She petitioned for her freedom, and a judge granted it to her and her family in 1856. She became a successful nurse and midwife, and gained a small fortune through real estate investments. She donated generously to charities and was instrumental in the founding of the First African Methodist Episcopal Church in Los Angeles.
    - Biddy Mason on Robert Owen's porch with daughter and friends. (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Biddy Mason and her family lived with Robert Owens when she first moved to Los Angeles. Her daughter Ellen married Robert Owen's son Charles.
    - Biddy Mason freedom papers (photographs)., 1856. (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Photographs of Biddy Mason's freedom papers. Certified copy received in 1860.
    - Biddy Mason property deeds and plots (photographs)., 1866-1867. (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Photographs of property deeds and plots purchased by Biddy Mason in the 1860s.
    - Mr. and Mrs. A. Dunbar. (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Photograph of the couple in front of their home on the outskirts of Los Angeles, which later became Inglewood.
    - C. W. Holder, rancher. (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Portrait from the Liberator, Jan-Feb 1904.
    - Southern California adobes granted to people of African descent., 1920-1936. (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Includes adobes on Rancho Rodeo de los Aguas (grantee: Maria Rita Valdez), Rancho Santa Gertrudes,
    - Early Los Angeles buildings and maps (photographs)., 1784-1888. (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Maps of early California Spanish ranchos, and maps that highlight those ranchos granted to people of African descent. Early photo of Los Angeles plaza, Sonoratown, residential streets
  - Other Individuals and Families in Early California.
    - James Henry Coleman and family. (Box 71, Folder 1)
    - Alvin Coffey and family. (Box 71, Folder 2)
    - Other early California families. (Box 71, Folder 3)
    - Peter Lester and family. (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - Delilah Beasley and Mary Ellen Pleasant. (Box 71, Folder 5)
    - Allen Light. (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - Peter Johnson. (Box 71, Folder 7)
    - Ed Johnson, butler of Mary Ellen Pleasant. (Box 71, Folder 8)
    - E.F. Josephs, photographer. (Box 71, Folder 9)
- Daily Life in Black Los Angeles and California., 1885-1980.
  Work, recreation, social organizations, churches, and civil rights groups.
  - Artists and Entertainers.
    - Dancers., 1950s-1960s. (Box 21, Folder 9)
      Includes photographs of Janet Collins, Carmen De Lavallade?, Josephine Baker, and Alvin Ailey.
    - Writers, Plays, Poets., 1917-1962. (Box 21, Folder 10)
      Includes portrait of Garland Anderson, first black writer to achieve Broadway production; photograph of an automobile sign promoting Anderson's play "Appearances;" photograph of King Lear production starring Frank Silvera and Roscoe Lee Browne; photograph of "Hiawatha's Wedding Feast and the Death of Minnehaha" with Thomas L. Johnson and Alice Reed; photograph of Langston Hughes reading his poetry accompanied by Buddy Collette's orchestra; portrait of young Langston Hughes.
    - William Grant Still, African American Classical Composer portraits. (Box 21, Folder 11)
      Includes several portraits of Still, including as a young man playing the cello and violin.
    - William Grant Still, conducting., 1936-1975. (Box 21, Folder 12)
      Photograph of Still directing the Los Angeles Philharmonic at the Hollywood Bowl (both 1936 and 1967); conducting the Seattle Youth Orchestra in 1968; Still with W.C. Handy and Samuel Brown at Jefferson High School (negative); and Still at reception in his honor at University of Southern California, 1975. Also includes ad for three-act opera, "A Bayou Legend" written by Still.
    - Parents of William Grant Still., 1880s?. (Box 21, Folder 13)
      Portraits of William Grant Still Sr., and Carrie L. Shepperson.
    - "William Grant Still, Composer" from Miriam Matthews' Binder. (Box 21, Folder 14)
      Includes portraits and snapshots of Still; photographs of African American orchestra and musical theater company; Still working at Pace and Handy Music Co.; Still at press conference for Second Baptist Church Choir concert; and other unidentified portraits and snapshots/
    - W.C. Handy, blues composer and musician. (Box 21, Folder 15)